<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The freedom of the fair sex asserted: or, Woman the crown of the creation In a letter to a young lady.</title>
            <author>Philgynes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23222</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827078</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207500</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240911559</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2125B</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827078</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827078e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1885:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The freedom of the fair sex asserted: or, Woman the crown of the creation In a letter to a young lady.</title>
                  <author>Philgynes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by J. Nutt, near Stationers Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCC. [1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Philgynes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Women --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207500:1"/>
            <p>THE FREEDOM OF THE Fair Sex ASSERTED: OR, WOMAN THE CROWN OF THE <hi>Creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a LETTER to a Young LADY.</p>
            <q>Jamdudum gratum est, quod Epistola nostra recepta Spem facit, hoc recipi me quoque posse modo. <bibl>Ovid.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>J. Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers Hall.</hi> MDCC.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207500:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207500:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:207500:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207500:3"/>
            <head>THE FREEDOM OF THE Fair Sex ASSERTED.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR Commands can never Fail to Oblige barely by being Yours; the Relation is so Indearing, and they derive such Charms from their Original. You Trust not howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to these borrow'd Beauties, but Endow them with intrinsick Excellence; like First Principles, they are Embrac'd as soon as Propos'd, for the Reason of them is self Evident.</p>
            <p>One would Contemplate the Ladies, methinks, of meer Choice, and not wait for an Obligation to intend so Divine a Subject; especially, <hi>Madam!</hi> who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207500:4"/> has the Advantage of Knowing You, and can thereby inrich his Mind with so bright a Train of Ideas. But when moreover, You Require it, Will not the very Stones Obey! Will not Matter it self dissolve into Meditation!</p>
            <p>I am a wonderful Instance my Self, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of your Power; that never Thought in my Life, but upon your Account; and never Thought of any thing beside You, but at your Command; even what I am now doing for its Birth, acknowledges your Authority; and for its Success, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ends upon your Influence.</p>
            <p>Of all the Parts of the Creation that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through Ignorance or Humour, none suffer so notoriously as the Ladies; and the Reason is because the same degree of Contempt, consider'd absolutely, and in it self, is lessen'd or aggrava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> alwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Proportion to the real <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of its Object; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, when the best things happen to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ur'd, the Injury they Receive must needs be gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>r than if it were Offer'd in the same manner to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ose of inferior Account: This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is which makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Sinful; tho' indeed, every thing Perfect in its Kind, ought to be held in a manner Sacred; and what has no Fault, cannot be Censur'd without a great One.</p>
            <p>This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Usage of the Ladies, is carried on Two ways; either by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207500:4"/> Raillery, or by more Serious and Settl'd Invectives: And accordingly 'tis pursu'd by Two sorts of Men. Those who take up with the former, are such as Behave not upon Principle, and with Sobriety, but give only a Loose to Censure, and Detraction, without any manner of inward Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice or Dislike. Nay, so far are they from that, as to Admire at least, if not Adore, the Party they so much Decry; which nevertheless they do, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent a Taste Forsooth of their great Wit, and give an agreeable Relish to Conversation. 'Tis their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness to Interpret every thing in the worst Sense it will bear; and if it will not admit an ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, yet they scruple not to make it Nonsense, choosing rather to Discover their Hypocrisy, than Conceal their Folly. Thus with them, all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Conduct and mutual Respect, observ'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ladies, is meer Emptiness and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; a little Freedom of Talk with our Sex, is down-right Impudence. Innocence of Behaviour is all Trick and Design, and Modesty no more than Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation. In Short, as every Vertue has its Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, so every Woman that appears Vertuous, has, nothing of it, they suppose, besides the Appearance. This Practice looks abominable, at first sight, and carries Guilt in its very Countenance. 'Tis a plain Composition of Hypocrisy and Vanity; and there is no third Ingredient can possibly make the whole more Odious than it is. As for those who engage in such a Conversation as this, they can have no Hopes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207500:5"/> to be sure of finding Favour at the Ladies Hands. (and that's a lamentable kind of Despair indeed) And for what is Future, they must be left with a Company of Pagans to the meer Mercy of Heaven. Nor will this look Extravagant, after Considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Main of all modern Wit is made up of Blasphemy against GOD, and Raillery upon Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: And, can it be unreasonable to Conclude each Vice of a like Nature, when they are both found so close in Company together?</p>
            <p>But, the Design of this Letter, if so Small a Trifle may pretend to any, is not to Expose such as Wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Misrepresent the Sex, (it would be unpardonable Presumption to attempt any thing of that Nature, which they themselves have already perform'd with so good Success) but to Rectify the Judgment of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who innocently enough. Misunderstand it; and express a much less Dislike at the General Conduct of the Ladies, than they retain in their Minds upon that Account. This, in a great measure, is owing to an Original Mistake about the proper Duty of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and what her Obligations are in the common Circumstances of Human Life. For, let her ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Deportment never so exactly Answer her real Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; yet, if that be once Mistaken, it's plain, the whole Course and Tenour of her Actions will be Condemn'd. And, 'tis no new thing among us, first to lay down false, or uncertain Suppositions of our own, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards wonder at the unaccountable Consequence.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207500:5"/>
            <p> That there is a Duty incumbent on the Side of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that she Naturally Owes us some sort of Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or other, is no more than what all Acknowledge. The Question is, in what Particulars, this Duty of hers Consists; and after what Manner, the Assistance she Owes, ought to be made good.</p>
            <p>'Tis a receiv'd Opinion, I know, that Woman is Born to Labour, and Oblig'd to Drudgery; that she is excus'd from no Difficulties Man is obnoxious to, but ought to share alike with him in all the burthensome Affairs of Human Life. Now, indeed, if the Duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, were an Obligation on her Part, to Comply with every arbitrary Injunction Man might Impose; or Submit to every extravagant Service he might Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, there wou'd then appear some colour of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for admitting this Doctrine; but certainly the Case is otherwise, and Women can never stand in the same Relation to us, with the brutish Herd: Their Province, in short, is quite distinct from ours, adapted to a Distinction of Nature and Abilities; and however by Compulsion or Compact, it comes to pass, that Woman frequently engages in Business, belonging peculiarly to our Sex, there are nevertheless, Visible Bounds set to her Obligations; and upon Nice In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry it will appear, she is oblig'd to no Particulars, (at least not in the same manner) as she stands rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Man, that he is oblig'd to, in his relation to her: So that tho' some kind of Assistance be due, 'tis made Payable however, in quite another manner, than has
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207500:6"/> been all along suppos'd, <hi>viz. In such a manner as will prove much more Easie and Natural to herself, as well as more Ʋseful and Advantageous to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us suppose it then, the proper Business of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to Cherish us with the Charms of her Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, to Compose our Tempers, and Soften our Manners; to Encourage our Hopes, divert our Fears, and Inflame our Affections; to make her self, in fine, every way Amiable; omitting nothing she may safely practise for our Ease and Happiness, without doing Violence to her own Nature: Tho' to say the truth, there is hardly need of such a Limitation; it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for her, to do us any Service by misemploying or abusing her Natural Powers; and she contributes not at all to our Happiness, so long as she continues to Impair her own. Hence it is, that this general View I have given of her Duty (how Unlucky soever it may prove in the end) promises at least Hopefully enough; wherein there occurs nothing to Displease the Ladies, nor any thing to Offend us: But the whole Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on their side is easy, and the Assistance it procures ourselves, compleat. For nothing testifies a Duty to be truly Stated so much as when it contains no Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor any thing Disagreeable, and yet fully answers the Ends of its Institution. How applicable this is to the present Case, will appear in the Conclusion of this Argument.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:207500:6"/>
            <p> What the original Condition of Woman was in the State of Innocence; and the particular Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of her Paradisaical Life; how large her Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and of what extent her Duty, is not easily discovered; that happy Scene being of no long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and but very little reveal'd relating to it. Whatever Obligations she might lye under in such a State, certain it is, they were such as arose from the nature of her Settlement, and such as the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, she was plac'd in, requir'd: But Those have been lamentably Chang'd from what they were; her Duty therefore consequent upon them, must necessarily change likewise: and since this great Revolution in her Affairs ensu'd upon the Fall, it will be by examining That, and a few Particulars at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it, that we must search out her present Duty.</p>
            <p>'Tis very remarkable, that the Curses of Heaven upon the Persons of fallen Man and Woman, were not denounc'd Promiscuously and alike, upon both; but Successively, and with notorious Distinction. First of all GOD addresses to <hi>Eve,</hi> and assigns her the particular Punishment of her Sin; that done, He addresses likewise to <hi>Adam</hi> (exclusive of his Wife) and Curses him accordingly. Now, I for my part, am not able to conceive, what Necessity there could be for so distinct an Address, unless it bore withal as distinct a Relation, nor to what purpose in the world there was a separate Cause, if they were to be shar'd both in common. Besides, if the Curses di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected only to the person of <hi>Adam,</hi> were by any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207500:7"/> means applicable to <hi>Eve,</hi> with as good reason those too directed to <hi>Eve,</hi> must have their influence upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his Male Posterity; and as soon as we Men begin to be Affected with hard Labour, and Sorrows in Child-bearing, the Ladies will in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, readily submit to all the Curses Heaven has inflicted upon us. If then, the Curses denounc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> in a separate and distinct man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, concern'd that Party and that alone, to which they were each of them so distinctly Directed; and it be the Duty of them both, to make Good the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Curses, or Commands, they were respec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively concern'd in (neither of which I presume can be deny'd) it will follow then, that Man only is oblig'd by his daily Labour and Industry, to Secure a necessary Subsistance, and provide all Accomodations of Life; and this, as well for the Woman; as for himself, for the Curse implying this Obligation is directed only to him, who by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can be the only Party concern'd in it.</p>
            <p>Hereabouts I look for an Objection to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, viz. That after all my Pains and Care, I have at Best but Struggl'd a little to determine barely, wherein the Duty of Woman, with regard to Man, does not consist; as for any thing like a Discovery, wherein it does, I have not made the least approaches towards it. I kindly undertake to excuse the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (however I come by authority to do it) from the more rugged and Ungrateful concerns of Life; but never think of Obliging them in the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207500:7"/> to more easie and acceptable duties. I take a tender Care to secure them from any Task which might Sully the Serenity of their Mind, or break in upon the Gaiety of their Humour; but yet provide them no other Business, consistent with the preservation of these. I have advanc'd, 'tis true, a kind of Paradox of my own; but, so wild a thing it is, I have already rejected it my Self, neither recommending it from reason nor enforcing it from authority; which looks at least, as if I were not so wedded to it, but I could well enough dispence too, with the Omission of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended duties it contains. And at this rate, the Sex is like to prove a very hopeful Assistance, bound to no Certain or Regular Performance, nor Determin'd by any thing but their own Humour: Besides, that in the Method I have hitherto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, 'Tis Impossible ever to Arrive at any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion in this Point; at least however to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate the duty of Woman, such as is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; For 'tis plain, there is not one Syllable of what I make her Duty to consist in, contain'd any where, in those Curses directed immediately to Her, out of which it was Infallibly to be Collected.</p>
            <p>In order to withstand an Attack of this nature, there is no more Requir'd than to consider.</p>
            <p>1st. Were there not the least intimation of the duty of Woman to be met with any were in Scripture; and had she no light from thence, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207500:8"/> Direct her in her deportment towards Man; 'tis yet very likely, she would, in such a case, have acted, after the same manner, that she stands now Oblig'd to from Revelation: my reason is, because she falls so Naturally into the exactest perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what proves to be her Duty; she Engages in it, even before she has time to make it her Choice, or can indeed well know what it is. So that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably matters would not stand in so very Deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a posture, even tho' she were left altogether to her self, both as to the manner and measure of assistance, she might think good to accommodate us with.</p>
            <p>2ly. It being first of all taken for granted, that the Sex owes us some sort of assistance, by determining once, wherein it does not consist, it is already determin'd wherein it does, viz. In the performance of every thing that can do us service, and is not Included under such determination. In plain words thus; it being prov'd, that 'tis no part of Woman's duty to assist us in a Servile and Laborious way; and it being granted at the same time on all hands, that she Ought to Assist us some way or other, what can remain, but it must be her Duty to do it in such a way, as is agreeable to her Inclinations, and proportion'd to her Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, viz, So as it has been before limited?</p>
            <p>Now, it would be needless to endeavour a proof, that She is in Duty bound to such a Method of Behaviour; for it appears necessarily so, in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207500:8"/> very nature of the thing. It would be endless to descend to particulars in it, because of their great vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, arising from so various circumstances, viz. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity of Time and Place; of Persons, and Humours, &amp;c. Each of which, as they differ, will require a quite different management, and application.</p>
            <p>3ly. By examining the Curses denounc'd upon both Sexes; their import, and particular direction, we may gain indeed a partial knowledge of their respective duties, viz. So far as they fall under the nature of a Curse. But then it were Madness by the same means to expect any further positive information. Woman, we all know, was Created for Man's Assistance, which Assistance therefore it became her duty to afford him, not as being a Curse upon her (for such it never was) but as it was made one end of her very being. Now as there were more, and greater ends propos'd herein, than the meer service of Man, so her behaviour ought to bear an agreeable proportion to them. Her duty to Man in the state of Innocence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted only of such actions as suited with her own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, at the same time that they answer'd his occasions. For it cannot without the greatest Impiety be Imagin'd, that God would require of her ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unnatural, or unnecessary Performances, that he would design her for his own glory, and the good of Man, and yet make her miserable in her Self, and a Burden to the rest of the World. 'Tis true, the Fall of Man occasion'd an extraordinary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207500:9"/> Change in his affairs; his former blessings withdraw, and Curses descend, thick upon him; yet we no where find him depriv'd of the Society, and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of his fair Consort; but when he is driven out of the blisful Gardens, she takes him by the hand, Wipes away his Tears, and qualifies the Bitterness of so sad an Exile. And the same Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that proves her Assistance, was to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd to us after the Fall, will serve to show it Ought to be Manag'd in the same Proportion as before, viz. With a Just Regard to her own Nature, as well as our present Necessities. These are two Essential properties of that Assistance, we can in Reason expect from her: and what has been Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered here to this purpose, has the Advantage of them Both; Wherein is included nothing to the Prejudice of her Faculties, or in Contradiction to her Inclinations; which implies all the service she can doe us, and what is sufficient to make us happy. Every thing beyond it is Grievous in the Performance, and Unprofitable in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion. To Illustrate this, but with one Instance; what would be more unnatural than an Army of Beautiful Ladies? The softness, and Delicacy of their Bodies disables them from Bearing Arms; and the tenderness of their Affections, Indisposes them for Blood and Ruin; their Limbs made only for Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orous Embraces, will soon Sink under the rude Encounters of War. Their Eyes may not wound to Death in the Field; and their strongest Charms
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207500:9"/> may Fail of Captivating a Barbarous Enemy. Such considerations as these have Justly Secur'd them from the Toil and Fatigue of this Employment. And there is no Need of going Far for Argument, would that Effectualy release them from every other Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>easie and Afflicting work.</p>
            <p>The natural Insufficiency of Woman for these things, directs Plainly to what she is truly capable of. For these Qualities, as Useless, and Insignificant as they appear to Some Purposes; Become yet Wonderfully Serviceable in a Different Respect, and Directed to a Proper End. Thus what can Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute more to the Improvement of Human Life, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by adding to the Pleasures of Enjoyment, or by taking off from the Burden of Evil Accidents, than a Pittiful and tender Companion? One who Condoles our Calamities, Rejoyces at our Welfare, and Sympathises with every Passion: One who Charms with no more than a Transient Glance, and Creates no less than Transports in common Conversation. What then are the Effects of her more familiar, and affectionate Behaviour, of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Little Endearments, Fondnesses, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resses! These are the Labours of Woman's Life; these the Instruments of Man's Happiness; thus employ'd she answers one end of her own Creation, and helps to Compleat the Design of His.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:207500:10"/>
               <head>WOMAN THE CROWN OF THE <hi>Creation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHAT has been already Confirm'd in the former part of this Letter, concerning the Nature and Extent of that Assistance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd us in the Creation of Woman, will be yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Recommended, by considering how Admirably well she Stands qualified for the Discharge of those Particular duties it Implies. This may be done, by taking a slight Survey of her Original Endownments, and acquired Virtues; which will at once Vindicate the Perfection of the Female Nature, and serve likewise to regulate our expectations of Advantage from it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:207500:10"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>I.</hi> EDƲCATION.</head>
                  <p>The Main of Woman's life depends much upon the manner of her Education: In order therefore to Declaim against the former with any Colour of Reason, or carry on the Design with any hopes of Success, the latter is first of all to be Condemn'd.</p>
                  <p>The common method of Educating young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men is frequently Impeach'd under the Specious Accusation of Vanity. And 'tis here Just as in other Cases; we soon Agree in the Censorious part, to call something Vain, but then as to the Rational, we are all Strangely Divided in our Opinions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Vanity of it does Consist; a good Argument this with me, that the general Conclusion is Rash and Unreasonable. For when once an Opinion can be founded upon Reason, it has usually one and the same Foundation among all the several Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etters of it.</p>
                  <p>To determine any action truly useful, or Vain, Regard must be always had to its Ultimate end, and design; for without this the Instruments of procuring the very best of Blessings, which one would think, are the farthest from vain, will never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless be reputed such. And thus no kind of action whatever (while abstracted from its end) can Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly be free from Vanity: 'tis for want of this Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary Caution, that the Ladies are so hardly Us'd in the case before us. Were their Education, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207500:11"/> the Natural Consequences of it but Considered together and with one View, it would not appear to be Manag'd out of a Principle of vain glory, and ostentation, but industriously contriv'd for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of their Nature, and the recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their persons. Their Lessons are Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and only Resining a little upon the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Nature. They teach how to raise plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable Passions, and Produce agreeable Ideas, to touch the Sence, and Transport the very Soul; in a Word, the repeated Essays of their first Years, make the practice of their duty become Habitual to them, and they quickly commence Artists in the great business of their Lives.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>II.</hi> CONVERSATION.</head>
                  <p>Most of the Conversation between man and man, may be divided into Insipid, and Contentious; such as either affects not at all, or raises the worst of Passions. We were never design'd, it seems, to converse among our selves: <hi>It is not good,</hi> says the Text, <hi>that Man should be alone:</hi> but the Ladies, Heavens be prais'd, are Sociable, and there lies our Refuge. When we are prety well mop'd with listning to one another's Dreams; or enrag'd by mutual Contradiction; we may repair to them for refreshment in the one case, and in the other for peaceable Inspirations. Their words Disperse in cumbent Cares, and restore the Sickly mind; they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207500:11"/> civilize our Savage natures, and keep us from running into the Woods; they Quench the unruly heats of Anger, and Kindle the Kinder Flames of Love; they alter in Fine the whole Constitution, and make us easie within our selves, and affable to one another.</p>
                  <p>A great part of that <hi>Je ne scay quoi,</hi> or secret agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness in the Persons of many Women, may be well enough accounted for, I believe, in their Conversation. No Wonder we receive such a Multitude of Wounds without knowing all the while from whence they come: The cause is so very O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bvious, it scapes our nicer Consideration. <hi>Cupid</hi> lurks under the Tongue, Wraps up his Arrows in Delicious words, and then alass! he must needs Kill with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Expression. A Woman's Eyes indeed may set fire to a Heart; but when that's done, it is her Breath must blow it into Flame.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing Incredible in these, effects to One who is Acquainted never so little with the nature of Female Conversation. It is not Clogg'd with the heavy Circumstances of Business; nor made Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seous by Pedantry, and Affectation; it partakes of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing low, but Condescension; and all the Passion it admits is Love. 'Tis Infinitely Various, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting in it's Matter; full of Innocence, and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, recommended by good Language, and a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful air of Elocution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:207500:12"/>
                  <head>§. III. <hi>WIT.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Ladies, some of us observe, are not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally so Witty as our selves. A great compliment upon them, I take it, if it were but such in design: More cannot be said in so few words for their Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; true Wit indeed is an excellent gift, and conducive to noble ends; but that which usurps the name of it, and what we most judiciously val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue our selves upon, is nothing but the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a vicious and degenerate mind; serviceable only to the designs of Malice, and helps to bring peevishness, and the Spleen into Fashion.</p>
                  <p>The Ladies we find are always pertinent in thought, as well as happy in expression; and that is to be truly witty. But then they never recommend their parts at the expence of their Virtue, nor Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice private Conscience to publick Fame. In a word, if they are less witty than men, 'tis only because they are better natur'd; and we have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reason, methinks, to boast of our understandings, so long as we have great reason to be asham'd of our dispositions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>IV.</hi> BEAƲTY.</head>
                  <p>'Tis in vain to offer at a general Definition of Beauty, and it can never be describ'd in such a manner, as will answer every private conception
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207500:12"/> of the Thing: Unless it were first possible for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries to be reconcil'd, or all men thought alike of the same subject.</p>
                  <p>It is without question a Providential contrivance, that we are all made to think in a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from one another: the Advantage of it is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly visible in the case of Beauty, and our differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent conceptions of it. For did every Woman ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Equally charming in the Eyes of every Man; nothing, 'tis likely, would be able to set bounds to Lust and Debauchery, besides Death or Impotence.</p>
                  <p>The Blessings of handsom Women among us Bears, methinks, some kind of Resemblance with that of Manna to the <hi>Israelites.</hi> For tho' 'tis true every Particle of That, had a capacity, they say, of Suiting with every Palate; whereas 'tis not every Woman can make her self to be Admir'd of all; and so the comparsion Fails; there is nevertheless an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety of Beauties, for the like Variety of Conceptions; and the Parellel holds good in the main, viz. that Here, as well as in the Wilderness is Meat, for every Palate; only it may perhaps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, because it deserves indeed a little more pains to procure it.</p>
                  <p>I take care always, for my own part, never to decry any Woman for absolutely Ugly; because her person does not fall in with my particular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what is taking, and agreeable; for I make no doubt, but in all such cases, it Exactly answers the Idea, which One, or More have Fram'd to them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selves of a perfect Beauty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:207500:13"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>V.</hi> RELIGION.</head>
                  <p>The Ladies are not more unlike us in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Complexions, than in the Face of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: and 'tis to be fear'd They wou'd come off equally gainers by either Comparison. They seem to make more of the same Principles than we do, and Manage them to better Advantage. They preserve the Substance of Religion, and let alone what ever is Superfluous.</p>
                  <p>Female Education leads not towards any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Controversial parts of Divinity; and the Ladies are so many standing Arguments of the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that sort of Study. Controversie, they well observe, Confounds Instead of Confuting; and as it always supposes Heresy, so 'tis generally Productive of it. It is with good Reason therefore that they make no part in religious Disputes, and thence are better Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to look to their own Business, and less subject to Discraction amidst their Devotions: They find no occasion to Judge Uncharitably of others, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Secure a good name to themselves.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true there are Hereticks of both Sexes, and many Women are through a Pardonable easiness of temper Seduc'd into wrong Perswasions; but they rarely offer a Heresy to the World themselves, or stand in the Front of a Novel Sect. They are Deluded, I say, by wicked Men; but have no thoughts of returning the Pious Fraud. To conclude,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207500:13"/> however They may stand Disttinguish'd among Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by a difference of Faith or Profession; the Wonderful Innocence and Charity of their Lives will raise them ever above the rest of the Rational World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>VI.</hi> MODESTY.</head>
                  <p>Modesty is the Darling Attribute of Woman, the great Moral Distinction between her self, and Man. This it is, that Recommends her Beauty, and Invigorates every Charm; that upholds the Dignity of her Nature, and preserves the whole Circle of her virtues Inviolable.</p>
                  <p>To talk of immodest Women is Nonsence; there can be no such: For to loose their Modesty, they must loose a part of their Nature; and then they are no longer Women but Monsters: Consequently such as Degenerate in this particular, bring no Scandal upon the Sex, for they cease to be members of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>VII.</hi> LEARNING.</head>
                  <p>We are apt to be mighty full of our selves, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Score of Learning; which, yet is the most Imperfect of any thing about us, and affords In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite matter of Humiliation. It consists, for the most part, in senseless Words, and solemn Looks; in Doubts, and Disputations, in Pride, Prejudice and Error. These are the Distinguishing Attainments of our own Sex; and and such as give notable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207500:14"/> indeed of Triumph over the other. If we pretend to any real piece of Knowledge, which the Ladies are without; we do but discover our Pride without having any thing to support it; and become ridiculously Sordid even before Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session. They have the same Faculties of Soul with our selves, and the same Capacities of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding; otherwise I don't apprehend how they can be styl'd a <hi>Help-meet</hi> for Us: But 'tis their peculiar Glory that they make use of these with Discretion, and to good Effect. In a word, they have Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge sufficient to make their Lives useful, and their Ends happy: and all beyond this is toilsome in the pursuit, besides that there is no such thing as perfect Acquisition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>§. VIII <hi>LOVE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Love is the Foundation of Happiness, and it's Perfection: the Pleasures of Earth are owing to it, and so are the Joys of Heaven. The measure of our Happiness is proportioned to the Charms of our Beloved Object; for the more agreeable, That, the more intense our affections are, and Our selves by consequence, so much the more happy.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:207500:14"/>
                  <p> All Objects, Consider'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Amiable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> our Affections, we find, just to the same Pitch, nor Produce in us Equal Degrees of Pleasure. One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reason of this is, because they all Differ in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Capacity; and Consequently Act not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Minds in the same Manner, and with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual advantage; But Each according to it's proper Nature, and Subordinate Powers. Some, for Instance, gain our Affections purely upon the account of what they are in themselves; and by the Force of their Intrinsick, and Inherent Excellencies, without any particular Endearment, or further Recommendation; such are things Inanimate, as curious Pictures, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Edifices, and the like: or Even Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themselves; so far as they are only Propos'd to us with their Natural, or Necessary Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. Such Objects under so Imperfect a Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this, can at Best but provoke a very Feeble Passion, a Mixture perhaps of some Love, and more admiration. Other Objects advance with yet a strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Charm; such as in it self is more Powerful than all the Rest, and when in Conjunction with them, is Irresistable. These strike with a Double advantage; They not only shine with absolute, and Intrinsick Glory; but Voluntarily Exert It too. In short, they return our Love, and strengthen that Passion in our selves, by the Additional Powers of their own; and we become the very same thing to what we Love, which it's self is to us. This is the Time, when Mutual Desires of Union begin to grow
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207500:15"/> Furious, the Prospect of it is Transporting, and the Union it self Happiness Unutterable.</p>
                  <p>What has been observ'd of Love in General, will naturally introduce the following Reflection, Viz. That we Men are indebted to the Ladies, for the compleatest Happiness our present Constitution can admit. We cannot but Love, as well as Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, the Virtues residing in Female Minds: And the Curious and Delicate Structure of their Bodies will call ever for our Admiration. But then, when the Ladies Generously apply all these for our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Satisfaction, with what Flowing Joys must we be fill'd! with what Raptures die away! In a word, the Perfection of the Female Nature is more than enough to fill our extended Capacities; and the Personal endearments of Woman-kind are able to command our utmost Affections. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of their Love are Judicious, and consequently Affecting. They are so curiously manag'd, and with so much Art, that they become no less Acceptable in the smallest Trifles, than in matters of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Importance. Their Love is remarkably different from ours in two respects: It is not so soon Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, nor so quickly put Out. They don't gratifie with their warmest Affections on a sudden: but the Recompence is, where once they fall, they Flame, and Burn immoveably for Ever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:207500:15"/>
                  <head>§. <hi>IX.</hi> PRƲDENCE.</head>
                  <p>Prudence is a serious Consideration of our own Condition, and a constant Management of ourselves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the sence we have of it. The Ladies, it must be confess'd, exceed us in this particular as much as in any other. As for those who have not this conviction upon their Minds, they may be satisfyed by running over distinctly the several Circumstances, Relations, and Capacities, of almost any individual of the Sex, and observing her proper Care, and Prudential Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct thereupon: Her Devotion to Heaven, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity to Man-kind, Her Piety to Parents, and Affection to Children, Her Love to her Husband, Her Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to Servants, &amp;c. And afterwards by looking back upon their own Behaviour in some of the same, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellel cases, and observing the many Absurdities com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in each of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>§. <hi>X.</hi> DIVERSION.</head>
                  <p>'Tis a common Complaint among the Enemies of the Fair Sex, That too much of their Time is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207500:16"/> spent in Ease and Pleasure, and consequently too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it Reserv'd for Business, and the necessary Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Duty. Now this Objection will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear Frivolous, and of no Force, if we do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it's first Rise It proceeds from a mistaken Notion of Duty in General: These Men look upon Labour and Difficulty, as Things essential to the Performance of whatever is Commanded by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and imagine a Thing is then done Best, when it occasions most Vexation and Pains. Thus I have known some Persons pretend to a more than ordinary Share of Religion, only because they Tormented themselves, more than Others did, about it; and were Ready to Condemn all such as serv'd God chearfully, and took a more Rational Freedom in the innocent Improvement of Life. And thus I am perswaded it is with the Men I am now speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of. They cannot allow the Ladies to be doing their Duty, so long as they put themselves to no visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pain in the Prosecution of it; when at the same time the only way for them to do it Effectually, is to do it Delightfully, and after their own Humour. They are naturally Dispos'd to accomplish those Ends for which they were design'd; and they then take the readiest way to attain 'em, when they pursue them in a Manner most Easie and Pleasant to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:207500:16"/>
                  <p> What has a kinder Influence upon the Mind of Man than Woman Singing? What will sooner Raise his Drooping Spirits, or Slacken his stormy Resolution? What can we desire more than to hear the Voice of a Syren, and never feel her Violence? What Joys like those of being Ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sh'd with the Musick, without being Ruin'd by the Monster? The Ladies are all Sincere; their Songs full of Harmony and Love. And shall we be Offended at our own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, because the Authors of it are Partakers with us, and repeat with Pleasure what we hear with Transport? Shall we deny the Sweetness of the Charm, or not admit it to our Ears? O senseless Obstinacy! ó barbarous Stupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!</p>
                  <p>Again, Nothing adds a diviner Grace to the Person of a Woman, than a proper Motion, a becoming Mien. <hi>Aeneas</hi> was no longer Ignorant of the Goddess his Mother, than till she Mov'd: He knew her by her heavenly Gate.</p>
                  <p>There is not any thing more Affecting, among all the silent Endearments of the Sex. <hi>Cupid</hi> Rejoyces at a Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Match, and Triumphs at a Ball; and, shall we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Ladies for using such an Exercise? For my part, I see no place for Censure: Those who do, I remit to the former part of this Letter, where they will find, That the Life of Woman ought to be Easie, as well as Use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and she may very reasonably consult her own Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, even there, where she is principally promoting Ours.</p>
                  <p>Thus, <hi>Madam,</hi> have I attempted, your Commands, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Brevity, and Method, You were pleas'd to Recommend. I haue given you my Thoughts, wherein the proper Business of your Sex, so far as it relates to our own, does consist; and consider'd Briefly, how well you are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by Nature and Inclination for it.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:207500:17"/>
                  <p> The Conclusion of all is, That you Ladies were made to be Happy yourselves, and to make us so; and that as your own Happiness is the first End of your own Being, so 'tis the first Step too to the Happiness of ours.</p>
                  <p>This Argument might, I confess, be much improv'd by making use of different Considerations, and enlarging far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon each: But you guess'd aright of my Incapacity, and accordingly confin'd my Pen. Nor have I cause to Complain of the Restraint; for I have so shamefully ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd the Best Cause in this little Compass, that a greater Liberty could have only turn'd to my greater Confusion: But all this Acknowledgment of mine, is downright Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressing the Character of my own Sex. 'Tis much more Natural for us to be Conceited with our own Performances, to magnify a little Merit in our own Eyes, and then claim a Reward as Vast as our partial Imagination. You must needs be Sensible, <hi>Madam,</hi> of this common Infirmity among us; and I beseech you, Consider it: For there is nothing else, I know, of can excuse me, if in consideration of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Trifle, I presume to do my self so much Honour, as to Subscribe my self,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>your most faithful Servant,</hi> Philogynes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:207500:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>